Irving Allen Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Irving Allen Papers.
undated, 1960-1975.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Allen, Irving Lewis.
3 linear feet.
Irving Lewis Allen was born in Asheville, NC in 1931 and completed his undergraduate education at Morris Harvey College (1959). In 1964, he was appointed an instructor in the Sociology Department of the University of Connecticut. Dr. Allen was involved in the study of “New Towns”, a type of urban planning.
MSS19980149
Biography
CHRONOLOGY
1931 Born in Asheville, North Carolina
1959 Graduated from Morris Harvey College with B.A. degree
1961 Graduated from the University of Iowa with M.A. degree
1964 Appointed instructor, Sociology Department, University of Connecticut
1965 Graduate from University of Iowa with Ph.D. in Sociology
1967 Appointed Assistant Professor at University of Connecticut
1969 Appointed Associate Professor at University of Connecticut
1983 Appointed Professor at University of Connecticut
Scope and Content
The Irving Allen Papers consist primarily of printed research materials on “New Towns”. A type of urban planning, the “new towns” approach first became popular in England after World War II to alleviate overcrowding in London. The planning involves the creation of communities that offer housing as well as schools, fire and police departments, roads, local government and enough facilities and job opportunities for its residents.
The collection highlights research materials on British and American New Towns. Materials includes bibliographies, published volumes, a grant application and photocopied articles.
There are no personal papers in this collection.
Arrangement
Series I: Bibliographies and film lists ( 1960-1975 ) consists of four bibliographies and one film list.
Series II: Subject topics and New Towns ( undated ) contains photocopied articles on the following subjects as they relate to New Towns: policy and planning in the United States, policy and planning in the United Kingdom, social problems and social structure.
Series III: Publications ( 1960-1974 ) includes a research proposal and several publications.
Series IV: Specific New Towns ( undated ) is comprised of photocopied journal articles, publications and newspaper clippings grouped by location. Countries include: Australia, Brazil, Canada, Denmark, England, Finland, France, Germany, India, Israel, Italy, Netherlands, Pakistan, Sweden and the United States.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Allen, Irving Lewis. An Annotated and Classified List of 16mm Films on Urban Studies: New Towns, Urban Problems City and Regional Planning, Monticello, Ill.: Council on Planning Librarians, 1975.
Allen, Irving Lewis. The Effects of Community Structure on School Decisions: The Sources and Consequences of de facto school segregation in five Connecticut cities, Storrs: University of Connecticut, 1968.
Allen, Irving Lewis. The Inner City in Crisis: The case of Connecticut, Storrs: University of Connecticut, 1968.
Allen, Irving Lewis. The Language of Ethnic Conflict: Social Organization and Lexical Culture, New York: Columbia University Press, 1983.
Allen, Irving Lewis. “Mass Communication in the Urban Community.”, Ph.D. dissertation, University of Iowa, 1965.
Allen, Irving Lewis. Metropolitan Connecticut: A Democratic profile, (with J. David Colfax and Henry G. Stetler) Storrs: Institute of Urban Research, University of Connecticut, 1965.
Allen, Irving Lewis. New Towns and the Suburban Dream: Ideology and utopia in planning and development, Port Washington, NY: Kennikat Press, 1977.
Allen, Irving Lewis. Selected Bibliography on the Ethnic Groups of London, Monticello, Ill.: Vance Bibliographies, 1978.
Allen, Irving Lewis. Urban problems and Public Opinion in four Connecticut cities, (with J. David Colfax) Storrs: Institute of Urban Research, University of Connecticut.
Allen, Irving Lewis. Urban Sample Survey Field Procedures, Storrs: Institute of Urban research, University of Connecticut, 1967.
Allen, Irving Lewis. Urbanism in the modern Metropolis: Classified bibliography of selective Sociological approaches to urban ways of life, Monticello, Ill.: Council on Planning Librarians, 1970.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut--Faculty.
Subjects:
City planning.; Planned communities.
Document Types:
Notes.; Reports.; Publications.
Occupations:
Sociologist.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Allen donated his materials to the Special Collections Department of the University of Connecticut Libraries. They were transferred to Historical Archives and Manuscripts in 1979. The collection was moved to the Dodd Center in 1995 when Special Collections and Historical Archives and Manuscripts were merged to create Archives & Special Collections.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Bibliographies and Film Lists, 1960-1975
  - An Annotated and Classified List of 16mm films on Urban Studies, compiled by I. Allen, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - New Communities. A Bibliography, HUD, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - New Towns: A selected annotated bibliography, UNESCO, 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Other bibliographies on New Towns, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Sociology of New Towns and New Cities: Bibliography, compiled by I. Allen, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
- Series II: Subject Topics and New Towns, undated
  - Policy, planning—United Kingdom, undated (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Policy, planning—United States, undated (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Social Problems, undated (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Social Structure, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
- Series III: Publications, undated, 1961-1974
  - Alternative to Urban Sprawl, Legal Guidelines to Government Action, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Aycliff to Cumberland, A Study of seven New Towns in their region by Ray Thomas, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Britain's New Towns: An experiment in Living by A.C. Duff, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - “British New Towns” Town and Country Planning, v. 38, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - The Effects of Community Structure on School Decisions: The source and consequence of de facto school segregation in five Connecticut cities by Irving L. Allen, et. al., 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Evolution of a Community: A study of Dagenham by Peter Willmott, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - The Inner City in Crisis by Irving Allen and J. David Colfax, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Lake Europa, a New Capital for a United Europe, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Man and his Urban Environment by Fred Smith, [1972] (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - The Need of New Communities, a report on social provision in new and expanding communities, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - The New City: Architecture and urban research, an exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art, NY, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - New Communities, An American Institute of Planners Background Paper, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - “New Communities: Business on the Urban Frontier” Saturday Review, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - New Community Development. University of North Carolina, volumes I and II, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - “New Towns come of Age” Town and Country Planning, v. 36, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - “New Towns: Frontiers or Failures?” Building Research, parts I and II, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - New Towns: Laboratories for democracy. Report on the Twentieth Century Fund Task Force on Governance of New Towns, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - New Towns, a New dimension of Urbanism International City Managers' Association, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - New Towns in India by Ved Prakash, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Philosophic Basis for New Town development in America prepared by Monica Sending, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Rand Report: Urban Growth, New Cities and the population problem by Peter Morrison, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Regional New Towns: Alternatives in Urban Growth. A research project by Metro. Fund Inc. for our Metropolitan, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - “Research Proposal” by Arthur Shostak, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Social Development Work in the New Communities by Meryl Harrocks, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Symposium on Communities of Tomorrow. U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - United Nations Symposium on New Towns Moscow, 1964 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Urban Institute Report: New Communities and Growth Centers. By Harvey A. Garn, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
- Series IV: Specific New Towns, undated
  - Australia—Canbera (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Brazil—Brasilia (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Canada—Canadian Resource (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Canada—Don Mills (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Denmark see Sweden-Denmark (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - East Europe (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - Finland—Tapiola (Box 2:, Folder 43)
  - France-Italy (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Germany see Netherlands-Germany (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - Great Britain
    - England—Harlow (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - England—Hemel Hemstead (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - England—Letchworth/Wetwyn (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - England—Newton Aycliff (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - England—Peterlee (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - England—Stevenage (Box 2:, Folder 51)
    - Scotland—Highlands (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - India—Chandigarth (Box 2:, Folder 53)
  - Italy see France-Italy (Box 2:, Folder 54)
  - Latin America (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Netherlands-Germany (Box 2:, Folder 56)
  - Pakistan—Islamabad (Box 2:, Folder 57)
  - Sweden-Denmark (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - United States
    - Connecticut—Coventry (Box 2:, Folder 59)
    - Illinois—Park Forest (Box 2:, Folder 60)
    - Maryland—Columbia (Box 2:, Folder 61)
    - Minnesota—Cedar Riverside (Box 2:, Folder 62)
    - Minnesota—Jonathan (Box 2:, Folder 63)
    - Minnesota—Minnesota Experimental City (Box 2:, Folder 64)
    - New York (Box 3:, Folder 65)
    - North Carolina—Soul City (Box 3:, Folder 66)
    - Other U.S. new towns (Box 3:, Folder 67)
    - Pennsylvania—Levittown (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - Virginia—Reston (Box 3:, Folder 69)